<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A wonder vvorth the reading, or, A true and faithfull relation of a woman, now dwelling in Kentstreet who, vpon Thursday, being the 21 of August last, was deliuered of a prodigious and monstrous child, in the presence of diuers honest, and religious women to their wonderfull feare and astonishment.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842246</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842246</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 760:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A wonder vvorth the reading, or, A true and faithfull relation of a woman, now dwelling in Kentstreet who, vpon Thursday, being the 21 of August last, was deliuered of a prodigious and monstrous child, in the presence of diuers honest, and religious women to their wonderfull feare and astonishment.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Omens --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6887:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6887:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WONDER VVOORTH THE READING, OR A True and faithfull Relation of a Woman, now dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Kentſtreet, who, vpon Thurſday, being the</hi> 21 of August laſt, was deliuered of a prodigious and Monſtrous, <hi>Child, in the preſence of diuers honeſt, and religious-women to their wonderfull feare and aſtoniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of deformed baby</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>William Iones</hi> dwelling in Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſſe-ſtreete 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6887:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ILe broach no lye, paſt mans beliefe or reaſon,</l>
               <l>For that I would keepe cuſtome with the <hi>Seaſon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I Bring no newes here of ſome hideous <hi>Dragon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor tell I of <hi>Charles Starre-beſtudded Waggon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>New hurld from heauen: Nor of ſome <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Beare</hi>
               </l>
               <l>which' fore the King did one another teare:</l>
               <l>Nor of ſtrange <hi>Earthquakes</hi> ſwallowing worlds of people:</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Prophecie,</hi> found in ſome ruind Steeple:</l>
               <l>But here I bring (in a new true-borne <hi>Storie)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A monſtrous Meſſage</hi> ſent from the <hi>King of Glorie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:6887:2"/>
            <head>A True and faithfull Relation of a Woman, now dwelling in <hi>Kentſtreet,</hi> who vpon <hi>Thurſday laſt, being the</hi> 21 <hi>of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>was</hi> deliuered of a Prodigious and Monſtrous <hi>Child, in the preſence of diuers honeſt,</hi> and religious women, to their wonderfull feare and aſtoniſhment.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is reported of the famous <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian,</hi> that when he went foorth to warre againſt his enemies; it was his faſhion, firſt to diſplay a white Enſigne, as a token of his mercie, if his foes would yeeld to faire conditions: but if not, then would he diſplay a red En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, in ſigne of effuſion of bloud and threatning death and deſtruction: but if at leaſt they refuſed to ſtoope to his faire admonitions; then would he ſet vp his black banner: betokning nothing but reuenge, and bloudie ſlaughter; and that not one ſhould ſcape from his threatning furie. So hath Almightie God dealt with this our Country: hath he not from time to time ſent downe his Enſignes of anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs to affright vs from our ſinnes and to ſtope our fete in the way of Iniquitie, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, we goe one in our abominations? He hath deuoured vs with diſeaſes, pinched vs with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, terrified vs with accidentall fiers conſuming our houſes? he hath comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the mercileſſe waters to ſwallow the friutes of the Earth, ſo as they became
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6887:3"/>vtterly vſeleſſe and vnprofitable to you: he hath tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the ſeaſons, ſet Summer in Winters place, &amp; Winter in Summers ſtead: He hath called from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, the Noble, graue, and learned, the wiſe, the iudge, &amp; godly: nay hath he not come nearer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; and called the husband from the wife, the wife from the husband? the child from the mother? the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Sonne, one friend from another, and ſayd them all vp together in the graue of corruption by the hand of death to your ſad ſorrow and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? Theſe, and many moe Iudgements hath God ſent downe amongſt you, as ſo many Heralds to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme his iuſt anger againſt you for your abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and yet you lie ſnorting in your ſinnes, quaffing downe iniquitie like water, and ſecurely ſtreching your limes vpon the bed of luxuritie, as if God were not iealous of his honour, and regarded not our tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. <hi>O England, England,</hi> delude not thy ſelfe with theſe goulden dreames? but reſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that God will come, and viſit thee in ſome ſharper meaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd manner, then heretofore he hath done: the axe is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready laid to thy roote? his powerfull hand hath long beene heaued vp ouer thee, and when it fals, it muſt be thy confuſion: O remember, that God is ſaid, to haue feete of Lead, and hands of Iron, he is ſlow to wrath; but when he ſtrikes, he paies home and heauie. Therefore abuſe not thou Gods patient.</p>
            <p>How many warning peeces of his diſpleaſure hath he diſcharged vpon thee (O <hi>England</hi>) and yet, thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt no warning. What blazing Comets, what Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6887:3"/>what vnnaturall Inundations, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuolent Coniuntions of the Starres? what Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies againſt our King and State? What miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, Monſtrous, and Prodigious births haue beene preſented to our eyes, as hideous ſpectators of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie? yet all theſe cannot moue vs from our wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe? For better confirmation here of, and meeting with ſo faire an occaſion; I will briefely relate a moſt ſtrange and mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous accident in nature, which, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in mans apprehention, it may ſeeme unpoſſble. Therefore, leſt any ſhould meet my diſcourſe with a ſcoffe, and ſmilingly ſay? This is an vſuall tricke put vpon the world for profit? and that this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Childe birth (whereon my preſent ſubiect is chiefly grounded) was begotten in ſome monſter hatching brayne; produced for a Bartlemew faire ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie; and ſent at this time (for order ſake) to be nurced at the common charge of the newes affecting multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; let them know, that not one ſyllable ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the making vp of an vntrueth? but as it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued to be true, by the atteſtation of many godly, honeſt, and religious women? ſo no leſſe faithfully &amp; truely will I relate it, to the generall ſatisfaction of all thoſe that read. And in briefe, thus it happened. In Kent-ſtreete there dwelleth one, whoſe name is <hi>Iohn Ladyman?</hi> whoſe wife (vpon the 21. of <hi>Auguſt 1617.</hi>) after long travell, was deliuered of a Female child with a halfe forehead, without any ſcull, hauing a faire proportioned body from the breſt downward: the ſaid child had its mouth &amp; eyez miraculouſly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6887:4"/>in the ſayd halfe forhead neere vpon the breaſt, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid halfe fore-head lay a peece of fleſh of two fingers thicke round about, the fleſh being wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully curled like Gentle womens attire: being of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blew coullour like a turcke Cocke, the eyes being very bigg ſtaring and very firy red, which greatly terrifyed the midwife and all that were preſent, the chid being dead, the midwife labored to cloſe the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eies but could not, they preſently fell all to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer deſiring God to take from them this ſo ſodayne aſtoniſhment and feare, the midwife after prayer ariſing, and ſo the reſt of the women, beholding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne the Child, they ſaw the eares of it faſtened to the halfe forhead, not being like to Chriſtians eares, but ſtood pricking vp, behind each eare, was two lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bones ſtanding vp ouergrowne with fleſh, and hauing very long heaire. In this hideous and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full forme was this child brought forth aliue, to the great aſtoniſhment of the beholders, and grieuious lamentation of the parents; If any curious cenſurer call in queſtion the trueth hereof, let him e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quire at the place before recited, for his better ſatiſfaction: In the meane time let me thus ſtop his mouth: That he, who bad the Sun retire, &amp; it obeyed: that he, who rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp the diuided waters like walls of bricke? and maide a pathway through the deepe: that he, who graſpeth the thunder in his right hand, and the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow in his left: that he, whoſe thro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is heauen? whoſe footeſtoole is earth? that this terrible God, I ſay, who created all of nothing, can as eaſily diuert the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6887:4"/>and orderly courſe of procreation, into dreadfull and hideous deformitie. Therefore let me induce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery honeſt heart, to apply this to his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſeriouſly to weigh and conſider the ſinnes of the land in a holy conſideration? then ſhall he cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerne this monſtrous production, to be a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meſſage ſent from the Almightie, for our further admonition and inſtruſtion. And thou O <hi>London,</hi> that art intituled the beauty of the world, the blazing beacon of <hi>Europe.</hi> That in the midſt of iudgements, God hath allwaies remembred mercy, and hath not ſuffered, of a long time, his wrath to lie hard and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, and further that thou ſhouldſt not reach foorth thy hand to iniquitie? he hath indowed thee with many great and infinite fauours, turning thy fickneſſe into health, thy penury into plentie, thy mourning into mirth? and moſt aboundantly (out of his gratious goodneſſe) hath diſperſed the glourious light of his word, both in the publike Miniſtrie, and priuate excerciſes thereof, whoſe all-ſpreading luſtrie breakes foorth (like the ſwallowing of the Sea) in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſtreet, yet ſtill thou hateſt to be reformed: Thus hath he led thee with the lines of his loue, to walke more vprightly with him, who is the God of thy life, libertie, health, wealth and peace: and yet for all this (O <hi>London</hi>) art thou miſted by the malice of Sathan, and thyne owne corruption, miſerably deceiued with the pleaſures of ſinne, which laſt but for a moment: and ſtill doeſt thou lift vp thy heeles &amp; hands againſt God: and ſteeleſt thy heart, &amp; face, againſt his wayes,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6887:5"/>workes, iudgement, and mercie. No man takes heed to his paths: he that was filthie, is become more fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie: and the crew of the abominations (vnder whoſe burden the earth groanes: and men ſhould mourne if they were not ſenceleſſe, and graceleſſe) are ſo farre from diminiſhing, that they infinitly increaſe, and get head ouer thee. What need I poynt out vnto thee, thy pride, extortion, oppreſſion, briberie, vſurie, with the reſt of thoſe crying ſinnes? giue me leaue to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: why the very ſtones in thy ſtreets, beaſts in the fielde, all dumbe &amp; inſenſible Creatures, doe in their kinde, ioyntly crye out againſt thee, as the prophet did in his daies: Iuſtice is turned into gall &amp; worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, the poore are ſould for ſiluer, and the needy for ſhooes, why ſhould I capitulate, thy great pride and exceſſe in apparell for backe, with attyres for head, thy whoredome, luxurie, drunkenneſſe? (ſinnes dayly committed, in the preſence both of God and man, as though the Magiſtraite had no law to puniſh them: nor the Miniſter courage to reproue them: for feare of offending a great man in his pariſh, or looſing part of his pention. Thus doth the Snake deuour the Toad, and the Toad the ſnake: thus one wicked man ſtriues to Canopie the wickedneſſe of another, leſt his owne ſhould be vnmasked and laid bare. As for that fearefull ſinne of prophaning the Saboth, that is ſlighted off with the title of Recreation: O where ſhould one find that man, woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or child who with care and conſcience ſanctifies the Saboth day? either by their religious and reuerent preparing of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6887:5"/>themſelues to come to the publike aſſemblies? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, to demeane themſelues as beſeemeth ſuch heauenly exerciſes, as prayer, and preaching? who regards, to ſpend the holy Saboth in meditation, and conference of inſtructions publickly taught: in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pſalmes, Prayer, in viſiting the ſicke, in doing workes of charitie and Chriſtian loue? Or who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth not publikely prophane it, priuatly abuſe it: ſome holding it to be but a day of bodily reſt, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore betake themſelues to their pillow, and ſleepe lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then on any day of the weeke: ſome accounting of the Church aſſemblies, and the religious excerciſes therein, no better, then of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meetings for ſports: nor receiue the word with no more reuerence &amp; atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then a prophane Stageplay, or winters tale: ſome ſitting idly at their doores, gaping and gaſing: ſuffering, nay, commanding their ſeruants and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to prophaine it, by dancing, ſtoole-ball playing, with the like vnlawfull and wicked recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: ſome alſo poaſting ouer their worldly affaires, caſting vp their accounts: telling of money in Sermon time, reparing to Iuſtices for execution of Law, banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their kinſfolkes? with a thouſand ſuch like abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, fearefully committed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords day?</p>
            <p>For theſe (O <hi>London</hi>) may not I (with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) cry out in the bitterneſſe of my ſoule: Shall not the Land tremble for this? and ſhall not euery one mourne that dwelleth within thee? The which to preuent then, O let my admoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t beate vpon the Anuile of thy heart, and force thee to fall low vpon the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6887:6"/>knee of ſubmiſſion: repent thee betimes, while it is called to day, ceaſe to prouoke thy Maker with obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ambition: thy ſinnes are at full height, and with open mouthes call for vengance and deſtruction to conſume thee: O ſend out thy prayers &amp; repentance to ſtop the violence of the Lords iuſt anger breaking foorth againſt thee, which (as a ſtarued Lyon) waites at thy dores, and watches in thy higheſt ſtreets, to deuoure thee, &amp; to ouercloude thy beautie in darke, comfortleſſe, and wofull deſolation: The which, God of his gracious mercie, and fauourable goodneſſe towards thee, preuent in his due time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="envoy">
            <head>Iudicious Reader,</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IVdge mildly: &amp; what faults thou meetſt with, mend.</l>
               <l>For in two houres, this had both birth, and end.</l>
               <l>Aſſe, for the foule-toung'd ſpeller, I not feare him;</l>
               <l>Let him ſcoule, ſcoffe, and ſcold, I ſcorne to heare him.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:6887:6"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
